Where's Wu Lingsu?
吴灵素人呢
Look at the stone tablet.
看这石碑
It's the handwriting of the late emperor.
先皇御笔
(Dismount from Horse) No matter who you are,
不管你是何人
get off your horses.
下马说话
The calligraphy is poorly written.
这字也不怎么样
Presumptuous.
找死
Take position.
布阵
Shenxiao Sword Array.
神绡剑阵
Who would like to break it?
谁破一个给我看看
Maybe someone else.
还是换人吧
He can't break the array.
他可破不了神绡剑阵
He surprises me.
这小子是不是变强了
The move he used was Chixia.
用的是赤霞剑诀
Is it a sophisticated move?
很高明的剑术吗
I doubt it.
高明个屁
It only works
靠气血内爆
by exhausting qi and blood.
才借来一点力气
The more he uses it, the more badly he gets hurt.
用得越多
People who practice the move
练这个的
don't live long.
都活不久
How did he learn it?
他怎么学会的
His Lordship taught him.
王爷给他的
Did Xu Xiao trick him?
徐骁诳他
Doesn't he know
他不知道
the move may take his life?
用这功法会害他自己性命
He knows.
知道
Have you made up your mind?
你真的想好了
Though the swordplay
此剑法
is powerful,
虽然威力很大
people who practice it
但凡是练它的人
die quickly.
死得都很快
As long as I can exchange a slim chance of survival for Lin Family
若我用命来拼
with my life,
能换林家一线生机
I'm willing to die
我死千万次
thousands of times.
都心甘情愿
Give him.
给他吧
Let's bet
咱们猜猜看
how long can he hold out.
他还要撑多久会油尽灯枯
My guess is
我猜
two hours.
一个时辰
Give him a hand.
帮他破阵
Me?
我
If Your Highness
世子说什么
says so.
就是什么
- Despicable.
卑鄙
He has to fight all of you by himself,
你们这么多人打他一个
yet you think we're despicable?
还说我们卑鄙
I don't think it's fair.
没道理吧
It was Yuxiao Array just now.
方才是玉霄阵
Now it's the real
现在才是真正的
Shenxiao Sword Array.
神绡剑阵
It's powerful.
很强
Only God of Sword
唯有李剑神出手
can break it.
方能破阵
Don't you take action?
你不出手
I will if you take me as your master.
你拜师我就出手
Forget it.
不出手拉倒
Let me try.
我也试试这剑阵
Your Highness.
世子
Don't put yourself at risk.
切莫以身试险
I made the trouble.
是我惹的祸事
I can't just look on.
不能躲在一边
I'll fight with you.
我陪世子冲阵
Your Highness.
世子
The dead and wounded have been sent back.
死伤者已送回北椋
Fengzi Battalion report for duty.
宁峨眉率凤字营归队
Just in time.
来得正好
Stone tablet left by the late emperor.
先皇留下的石碑
World-famous Shenxiao Sword Array.
天下闻名的神绡剑阵
Dare you break it with me?
敢不敢陪我冲个阵
Take position.
列阵
Who are you, if I may ask?
阁下到底是谁
Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年
Son of Lord of North Liang?
北椋世子
(Mount Qingcheng) We're in Qingcheng instead of North Liang.
这清城不是北椋
You invaded our place.
你率众闯山
What do you want?
到底想要什么
There is a bandit called Old Meng,
有个叫老孟头的土匪
a little girl called Xiaoque'er
还有一个叫小雀儿的丫头
and a bunch of bandits following Old Meng.
再就是和老孟头一块儿的山贼
I must find them all,
有一个算一个
no matter dead or alive.
活要见人死要见尸
We've never seen them.
没见过
I have nothing to say, then.
那就没得谈了
Mr. Xu.
徐哥哥
Xiaoque'er.
小雀儿
Wu Lingsu, Lord of Qingcheng.
清城王吴灵素
You've come all the way.
世子远道而来
Why don't you come with me
何不入清城山
(Lord of Qingcheng Wu Lingsu) to enjoy the mountain scenery?
观赏山色
Fine.
好
You can
世子一人
come alone.
入我清城山即可
Please don't.
世子不可
OK.
好
I'll go by myself.
我一个人上去
You've had a long day.
辛苦了
You can retire now.
都退回去吧
We haven't arrived in Qingzhou yet.
还没到青州呢
You can't die.
你不能死
Of course.
当然
Get ready.
做好准备
If anything goes wrong,
如有变故
flatten the mountain.
马踏青阳
Is he out of his mind?
这小子是傻了
He goes alone, really?
真的就一个人进去了
Girl,
你这丫头
aren't you worried?
也不担心啊
He is a hundred percent safe.
万无一失的局面
Why should I be worried?
有什么好担心的
Are you sure I will save him?
你是说我肯定会出手救他
I'll bet you 500 coins
不如赌五百钱
that without your help,
徐凤年不用你出手
Xu Fengnian still can get out of the jaws of danger.
一样能化险为夷
He hasn't mastered the skill of using his blade.
这小子刀法还未入门
He can't do that.
不可能有这本事
Do you bet?
赌不赌
Yes.
赌
Shall we sneak in?
能溜进去吗
Here we are.
到了
Xiaoque'er.
小雀儿
Go inside first.
你先进去
You surprised me.
我没想到
Your Highness,
世子
you dare come in.
还真敢进来
Turn them over to me now.
把人给我
You ran the risk of
闯青阳派
provoking Qingyang Sect just for the village girl?
就是为了这个山野丫头
Make your bargains.
你开条件
Were the man and woman who broke the array
刚才为你闯阵的那一男一女
your guards?
是你的侍卫吧
They showed no respect to us.
对青阳派无理
I want them to die.
我要他们的命
Fine.
可以
Give me what I want.
把人给我
I'll turn them over to you.
那两个交给你
I want you to go out now
世子现在就出去
and take their heads to me.
把两颗人头拿来
That's not the deal.
买卖不是这么谈的
I'm not making a deal with you.
这不是买卖
Once you come to my place,
世子入了清城山
your life is in my hands.
命就在我手里
You have no choice.
你没得选
He didn't fall for the trap.
这就骗不下去了
What do you think he would do?
你觉得这小子接下来该怎么办
What he would do?
怎么办
Fight, if he fails to make a deal.
谈不了就打呗
Dare he fight against him?
他还敢动手啊
What's there to fear?
怕什么
It's Wu Lingsu who will find it hard
现在骑虎难下
being on thin ice.
是那姓吴的
Do you want to die?
你找死吗
I'll give you a chance.
我给你一个机会
Bring them to me.
把人给我
But your life
可现在
is in my hands now.
你的命在我手里
Fengzi Battalion is waiting outside your gate.
凤字营就在大门外
Everyone saw me
所有人都看见我跟你
coming with you.
进了青阳派
To kill me,
你想杀我
you'd better think
先想想自己有没有本事
if you're capable of killing all my men first.
杀光门外所有人
As long as one of them escapes,
只要走了一个
Xu Xiao will lead North Liang Cavalry here
徐骁就会带着北椋铁骑
to flatten the mountain.
踏平清城山
After killing you,
杀了你
I'll return to the capital immediately.
我即刻回京
I don't think Xu Xiao
我就不信徐骁
can catch up with me.
能飞过来找我
He doesn't have to.
不用飞
Your family will be turned over to North Liang.
京城会把你全家绑给北椋
You're lying!
胡说
They'll trade your family's life
用你一家性命
for Xu Xiao's retreat.
换徐骁收兵
It gains ten thousand percent.
一本万利
You lose.
你输了
You knew it in the very beginning?
你一早就明白这局面了
It's easy to guess.
这有什么难的
How dare they
区区一个青阳
kill the son of Lord of North Liang in public?
怎么敢明面里杀北椋世子啊
Does he come alone because
所以徐凤年孤身入山门
he has nothing to fear?
是有恃无恐
Yeah.
嗯
He is too cunning
这家伙贼得很
to risk his own life.
怎么会去送死
I didn't expect you to be his bosom friend.
没想到你是他的知己啊
Nonsense.
你才知己
You owe me 500 coins.
记得五百钱
You deserve your reputation.
世子
Lubricious reputation?
贪花好色吗
No wonder she keeps praising you.
难怪她一直夸你
Who do you mean?
谁夸我
What are you talking about?
说什么呢
OK.
行了
Bring them to me.
人你交给我吧
You can tell people in the capital
京城那边儿
that I bullied you.
就说我仗势欺人
The royal family won't blame you.
皇室不会怪你
No hurry.
不急
Someone wants to see you.
有人想见你
Old Meng isn't dead, is he?
老孟头没死
You're far-sighted
有眼光
with iron nerves.
有胆识
You're great.
世子很了不起
Aunt.
姑姑
Fengnian.
凤年
Zhao Yutai.
赵玉台
Do you know her?
你认识
I had been hiding under Tingchao Pavilion for years.
我躲在听潮亭底下好些年
Whenever Xu Xiao and his wife went to see me,
徐骁夫妻每次来见我
she stood by their side.
她都守在边上
Does she work for Xu Xiao?
她是徐骁的人
Do you know Xu Fengnian's mother?
你知道徐凤年他娘吧
Yeah.
嗯
She was the first person in the mansion of Lord of North Liang
王妃
who smiled at me.
是府上第一个对我笑的人
I still remember her.
我到现在都还记得
His mother's surname was Wu.
他娘姓吴
She came from the Wu family,
来自剑冢吴家
who was the last sword champion.
是吴家上一代剑冠
The sword masters of the family
吴家的剑主
all have their own swordsmen,
都有自己专属剑侍
who grew up with their masters.
与剑主一起长大
In that case,
这么说
she was the Consort's swordsman?
她是王妃的剑侍
She was a sister
名为剑侍
rather than a swordsman to her.
更似姐妹
No wonder he called her Aunt.
难怪叫姑姑
Don't be sad.
姑姑不哭
(Sword Tomb of the Wu family) I'm not sad.
不是哭
I'm happy.
是高兴
After my mother died,
当年我娘死后
you got disappeared.
姑姑就没了踪迹
Have you been imprisoned here by him ever since?
莫非是被他囚禁此处
He's my husband.
他是你姑父
Why did he do this to me?
这是怎么回事啊
During your travel,
当年游历
you made many friends.
你和他们相识
With your status,
你这身份
you've been watched by many people.
有许多人盯着
Those with ulterior motives may use your friends against you.
你的朋友就是你的弱点和把柄
I took them to Qingyang Sect
我把他们带到青阳派
in order to protect them.
也是为了保护他们
That's right, Mr. Xu.
是啊
They're very kind to me.
这里的人都对我很好
Then...
那
Where is Old Meng?
老孟头去哪儿了
They've been sent to
他们都悄悄地
North Liang.
送去了北椋辖内
Now,
如今
they have land.
有了田地
They're doing very well.
过得非常的好
Master said I'm talented.
师父说我有天分
I'm a disciple of Shenxiao Sect, too.
如今我也是神绡派弟子了
Have you taken my aunt as your master?
你拜姑姑为师了
Her master is your uncle.
她拜在你姑父门下
Wasn't he granted as Lord of Qingcheng?
可他不是皇室御赐的清城王吗
Qingyang Sect has been hostile to North Liang over the years.
这么多年青阳派仇视北椋
Isn't it real?
全是假的
It's our plot.
是反间
We keep an eye on the capital for North Liang.
替北椋盯着京城呢
Does Xu Xiao know it?
这事徐骁知道
Of course.
自然知道
You have a good talk.
你们俩好好聊着
I'll look around
我去周围看看
in case anyone will see you.
免得让人瞧见
Mr. Xu,
徐哥哥
see you later.
我待会儿再来找你
If anything I've been doing these years
我这些年做的事
leaks out,
稍有疏漏
it will cause a great disturbance.
就会天翻地覆
General dares not tell anybody
大将军不敢泄密
for fearing it might put me in danger.
也是怕我遇到危险
What a big plan.
真是大手笔
Qingyang Sect is actually on our side.
青阳派竟是北椋暗线
In the future, when our cavalry come out of North Liang,
将来铁骑若出北椋
they'll meet no obstacle at Mount Qingcheng.
清城山便是通途
It won't strangle our throat again.
再也掐不住北椋咽喉
Except for Qingyang Sect,
不仅仅是青阳派
I'm doing
我真正做的事
more important things.
比这更重要
Is there anything more important?
还有什么事能比得过这手笔
These years,
这些年
I've been investigating
我一直在查
your mother's murderer.
害了小姐的凶手
Ah.
啊
Who?
谁
Go, quickly.
世子快走
Aunt, don't worry.
姑姑没事
They're with me.
自己人
I don't care about
你家的事
what happened to your family.
我懒得听
Why are you there?
你怎么在那啊
It's the old man's fault.
都怪这老头
Is there a ladder?
有梯子吗
I'm going down now.
我现在就下去
Jiang Ni.
姜泥
A maid of mine.
我家丫鬟
Maid?
丫鬟
Like a concubine?
通房的
No.
不是
(Mount Qingcheng) He hasn't come out yet.
这还没出来
Shall we go in?
咱们冲进去
There's no need.
不用了
God of Sword and Jiang Ni are no longer in the carriage.
李剑神跟姜泥已经不在车里了
You mean...
你是说
They are already in probably.
应该已经进去了
Good.
那就好
God of Sword
剑神在
will ensure his safety.
世子可保无忧
Which one do you mean?
哪个剑神啊
Is there another God of Sword?
哪有第二个剑神啊
The one armed man, Li Chungang.
独臂的便是李淳罡
Isn't he dead yet?
他还没死啊
Not yet.
还没
Excuse me, sir.
前辈见谅
I didn't mean that.
我不是那个意思
Sir, may I ask
敢问前辈
where is His Highness?
世子呢
Inside.
里面
Then why did you come out?
那您怎么出来了
I had too much breakfast.
早饭吃多了
I'm a little sleepy. Let me take a nap first.
有点困
Don't worry.
放心吧
I left Jiang Ni there.
我把姜泥留里面了
What's the use of Jiang Ni?
这把姜泥留里面有什么用啊
Since Mr. Li is back,
既然前辈回来了
I don't think there would be any serious danger.
那应该是不会有什么大事
I'll retire, then.
那我先退出去了
You don't have to.
不用退
Aunt, go ahead.
姑姑接着说
You can tell her anything concerning me.
我的事不用避着她
You just said
您刚才说
you've been investigating my mother's murderer.
您一直在查害我娘的凶手
Yes.
是
I've been doing that
小姐过世起
since her death.
就一直在查
Did you find anything?
查出具体结果了吗
When your mother died,
小姐离世时
General and I
奴婢和大将军
found she was seriously wounded.
才发现她身负重伤
But she
可小姐
wouldn't tell us the murderer.
不肯说出害她的凶手是谁
The murderer must be powerful.
对手太强
My mother didn't want us to take revenge for her.
娘是怕报仇害了全家
Over the years,
这些年
I investigated the date step by step
我一步步排查日子
and examined the cause of her death.
细算因果
I can probably guess
大概能猜出
when she was wounded.
她何时受的伤
She once
当年小姐
went to the capital alone.
曾独自进京
She might
她的伤
get wounded during the trip.
应该就是那会儿留下的
When was it exactly?
具体什么时候
She was pregnant with you at the time.
那时正怀着世子
The murderer was in the capital.
凶手人在京城
Have you found who it was?
查出是谁了吗
Not yet.
还没有
I couldn't find anything.
一点细节都追查不到
But the result
可查不到
is very illustrative itself.
本身就是个答案
The murderer must be powerful enough
凶手权势滔天
to erase all the clues in the capital.
才能在京城抹去所有线索
General asked me to
大将军让我在清城
spread rumors
传出你姑父
in Qingcheng
采阴补阳的
of your uncle being lecherous.
好色名声
What's his plan?
徐骁这什么路数啊
He also asked me to pass some words.
大将军有话让我转告
He said,
他说
you don't want to take over North Liang
你不愿用大将军的方式
in his way.
接手北椋
Yes.
是
Did you kill
那些山匪
those mountain bandits?
世子杀了吗
Yes.
杀了
If it were him,
换作大将军
he would also kill them
他也会动刀杀人
to avenge the dead.
为亡魂复仇
Did he arrange that?
那些山匪是他安排的
Yes.
是
The government surrounded them from all sides
官府四面围堵
to force them to Qingcheng.
就是将他们逼到清城
Those bandits
这些人
were sent to test your ability.
是为世子试刀锋的
General also guessed
大将军还猜到
you would break into the palace alone.
你会孤身闯宫
He said in advance that
他事先就说过
your mind and means
这心机手段
were very much like his.
和他行事并无二致
He said you wanted to take a new path.
他说你想走一条新路
But in the end,
可到头来
you still took the path he had paved for you.
都在大将军为你铺好的路上
I know
我知道
you blamed him
世子始终记恨
on refusing to investigate your mother's death.
大将军不肯追查小姐的死因
But you must understand
世子你要明白
it involves too many people.
此事牵连甚广
We must keep it secret.
必须保密
I know.
我明白的
General said
大将军说
you were unwilling to kill,
你不愿杀人
but it turned out
可事实证明
when it was time to kill,
该动刀的时候
you wouldn't hesitate.
你一样不会手软
You and General
世子和大将军
are just alike.
其实本质是一样的人
No.
不
I'm not like him.
我和他不一样
I won't sacrifice my family.
我不会牺牲家人
It isn't my place
世子和大将军的事
to get involved between you.
我不便多说
But General told me,
可大将军和我说了
when you come up the mountain,
等你闯上清城
I must tell you all the clues I've found
我就把这些年
during the investigation.
追查到的所有细节都交给你
From now on, no matter how many years it takes,
从此以后无论多少年
even if General and I are dead,
哪怕我和大将军都不在了
you must follow up
可你一定要追查下去
and avenge your mother.
替小姐报仇
I'll follow up
他不说
even if he doesn't ask me to.
我也会查下去
Please wait a minute.
世子稍等
I'll get you something.
我去给你拿些东西
OK.
好
You hold on too tight.
抓得太紧了
Does it hurt?
疼吗
No.
不疼
I'm sorry.
对不起
Why didn't you remind me?
你怎么也不喊疼啊
Your mother was a nice person.
王妃是个好人
I remember when I first got to the mansion,
记得我刚进王府的时候
I was scared and sad.
既害怕又伤心
It was her gentleness
是她的温柔
that comforted me during the most difficult times.
让我缓过了最难的一口气
Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年
I'd like to avenge your mother with you.
我愿意和你一起为她报仇
But we're still bitter rivals.
但我和你还是照样势不两立的
Here are all the clues
这些年追查凶手
I've found
整理出来的东西
during the investigation.
都在里面了
When did you marry Wu Lingsu?
姑姑何时嫁给了吴灵素
Before I joined Shenxiao Sect.
在入神绡派之前就嫁了
Then we had Shizhen.
当时有了士桢
He is about your age.
他和世子差不多大
Where is he?
人在哪儿
In the capital.
在京城
Your uncle was granted as Lord of Qingcheng
你姑父被封清城王
and under orders to oppose North Liang.
授命与北椋抗衡
Outwardly, he is powerful.
说起来权势不小
Is he taken hostage?
是被当成人质
As long as my real identity is not revealed,
只要我的身份不拆穿
he'll be fine.
他就没事
We must find a way to save him.
得想个办法救他回来
You don't have to
他的事
worry about him.
世子不用担心
Read this thoroughly
你好好看这个
and burn it.
看完烧了
Where are you going?
姑姑去哪儿
I have some errands to run.
我有些事情去办
I'll come back soon.
一会儿就回来
Why don't you read it to me?
要不你读给我听
One coin per word.
还是一字一文
Are you crazy?
你疯了吧
Your aunt has been concealed her real name to investigate the case.
你姑姑隐姓埋名查了这么多年
It's important.
多重要的事
How can you let me read it?
你让我来读
It doesn't matter.
没事
Read it on yourself.
你自己看
What message did you send?
送的什么消息
How long has it been
我们有多久
since we last saw Shizhen?
没见到士桢
There's no one in the capital he can trust.
他一个人在京城无人可信
He carries his life in his hands.
随时都有亡命之险
Tell me what message did you send.
我问你送的什么消息
Details of Xu Fengnian's visit.
徐凤年此行细节
It was supposed to be sent to the capital.
这本来就要送去京城的
If we tell them
要让他们知道
Xu Fengnian broke the sword array,
徐凤年闯剑阵
they'll trust us more.
京城才会更相信我们的立场
What else?
还有呢
Layout of the North Liang barracks.
还有北椋的军营部署
Only by doing this,
用这个
could Shizhen come home.
才能换士桢回来
Her Grace treated me like a sister.
小姐待我如姐妹
I owe her
我这条命
my life.
都是她的
It's just the layout of barracks.
只是一份军营部署
Nothing confidential.
并不牵扯绝密
Who asked you to do this?
是谁让你这么做的
I don't need anyone to tell me
我救自己的儿子
how to save my son.
不用人教
You've been uneasy since last time
打士桢最后一次传书回来
when Shizhen sent a letter to us.
你就开始心神不宁
Did he ask you to do this?
是他叫你这么做的
He wants to escape the danger
士桢也是想逃离险地
and come home.
和我们团聚呀
Has Shizhen
士桢
turned to the royal family
在京城
in the capital?
有没有投效皇室
Of course not.
当然没有
Good.
那就好
Don't you want him to come back?
你就不想救他回来
Do you really want to
你真的要为北椋
sacrifice our son for North Liang?
献出儿子的命
General has left for the capital.
大将军已经启程前往京城
Did he tell you
他跟你说过
he would rescue Shizhen?
要救士桢回来
No, he didn't.
没说过
How can you believe him, then?
那你怎么信他
If General doesn't
如果这次京城之行
bring Shizhen back this time,
大将军没有带回士桢
I'll go to the capital myself
那我就亲自入京
to rescue our son.
救回儿子
If you really
如果你
sent the military intelligence
真要把北椋的军情
to the capital,
送去京城
I'd have no choice but to kill myself in front of Her Grace's tomb.
那我就只能在小姐的灵前自尽
Fine.
好吧
I won't send the letter.
我不送信
Don't tell Fengnian
这些事
about this.
不要讲给世子听
Have you done with it?
看完了
My mother's murderer
要害我娘的
was from the royal family of Liyang.
是离阳皇室
There's no concrete clue, isn't there?
不是没有具体线索吗
It recorded the time
这上面记载了
when my mother went to the capital.
我娘进京的具体时间
Two points.
两个要点
One,
一
she was just pregnant with me.
刚怀了我
Two,
二
Xu Xiao was about to be granted as the Lord of North Liang.
当时京城正要给徐骁封王
They had no choice
离阳朝
but to grant your father as the lord.
给你爹封王是无奈之举
He conquered the six kingdoms.
他扫灭六国
They couldn't convince the public if they didn't do that.
不封王天下人都会心寒
But the royal family
但离阳皇室
definitely didn't want North Liang to have a young master.
绝不希望北椋大军有一个少主
So my mother's pregnancy
所以我娘怀孕
was what they feared most.
是皇室最害怕见到的事情
It turns out your enemy is the royal family.
那你的仇人是离阳皇室啊
Yes.
是
Your father could draw the conclusion, too.
这结论你爹也能推出来
Why didn't he
他为什么不起兵
rebel against the capital?
杀进京城
If he rebelled,
北椋若反
the world would fall apart.
天下必将分崩离析
Numerous people would die.
又不知道要死多少人
For that reason, you give up taking revenge?
因为这个仇都不报了
No, I won't.
不是不报
I just don't want to take revenge at the expense of peace.
是不该拿天下做筹码
What do you mean?
什么意思
If they sent out troops at the time,
当年若真是出动大军
my mother couldn't leave the capital alive.
我娘不可能活着离开京城
I think they dare not
我想皇室
take action in public.
也没那个脸面明着出手
They must've tried to assassinate her.
是暗中截杀
My mother was the top talent
我娘是吴家剑冢
of Sword Tomb of the Wu family in nearly a hundred years.
近百年来第一天才
They needed a real master
要想杀她
to kill her.
定是高手
There might be more than one assassin.
恐怕不只一个
I'll find out the assassins who ambushed her
我会把当年伏击过我娘的人
one by one
一个一个找出来
and take their heads with my own hands
亲手斩下他们的人头
to pay homage to her.
祭奠我娘
One day,
总有一天
I'll go to the capital to find out the truth myself.
我会亲自去京城查明真相
Your mother left something to you.
你娘有东西留给你
What is it?
是什么
Follow me.
跟我来
I'll wait here for you.
我在这等你回来
It's far from Qingyang Sect, isn't it?
这儿已经离青阳派很远了吧
Qingyang Sect has attracted too much attention.
青阳派太瞩目
Her Grace preferred quietness.
小姐喜欢清静
What's this?
这是什么
Her Grace and I
我和小姐
were from Wu Family.
出自吴家
I know.
我知道
Sword Tomb of the Wu family was once the top sect of swordplay.
吴家剑冢曾是天下剑道之宗
Not anymore.
早就不是了
Li Chungang.
李淳罡
Deng Tai'e.
邓太阿
Jian Jiuhuang.
剑九黄
Top masters of swordplay emerge without end.
天下用剑强者层出不穷
The Wu Family
吴家气运上
has lost on fate already.
已然输了半筹
But it still has foundation.
毕竟底子还在
Foundation
有底子
and family rules.
也有规矩
Back in the time,
当年吴家
Her Grace wasn't allowed to be with General.
不许小姐和大将军相近
She broke up with her family
小姐和吴家决裂
and went to Liaodong on a white horse.
白马走辽东
So they finally got together
两人才走到了一起
and then they had you.
也才有了世子
The Wu family must be mad.
吴家一定气疯了
After the members of the family die,
吴家人走后
their swords should be returned to the Sword Tomb.
佩剑都要回归剑冢
But Her Grace
可小姐
was an outcast from her family.
已被吴家逐出家门
Her sword
她的剑
couldn't be sent back.
已经是回不去了
That's why
所以我把小姐的佩剑
I sealed up her sword here.
就封在此处
She told me before she died,
小姐走之前和我说
if you
世子
choose to practice martial arts,
若是选择习武
her sword
她的这把佩剑
would be left to you.
便交给世子
North Liang overran the whole world.
北椋纵横天下
Her Grace
小姐手中剑
(Daliang Dragon Sparrow) had defeated many heroes with the sword.
曾让天下英雄低头
Her Grace also said,
小姐还交代
if you
世子
meet a good girl one day,
若是将来遇到
who happens to practice swordplay,
恰巧习剑的好女人
the sword would be left to her as the betrothal present.
就当是小姐送的聘礼
I'm afraid I won't meet anyone
我怕是遇不到
like my mother.
娘亲一般的女子了
As long as you like her,
只要是你喜欢的女子
she is the best in the world.
便是天下最好
The big one in the mountain.
山里的大家伙
Are you Xiaoque'er?
你就是小雀儿
Big one?
大家伙
Is it a tiger?
是老虎吗
It's a monster.
是怪物
It's fair to call it a monster.
说是怪物也不为过
It's a strange beast in Mount Qingcheng
它是清城山的一只异兽
called Hukui.
名为虎夔
It's extremely fierce.
凶悍无比
Have you seen it?
姑姑见过
I once fought it.
交过手
It couldn't defeat me.
它奈何不了我
I couldn't defeat it, either.
我也奈何不了它
It's a fight.
是在争斗
How strange!
奇怪了
There's no beast in Mount Qingcheng that can fight it.
清城山并无野兽能与它对敌
Xu Fengnian
徐凤年
will be back soon.
等会儿就回来了
Mr. Xu is very nice.
徐哥哥人挺好的
He taught me to blow leaves.
还教我吹叶子
I thought at the time
当时我就想过了
I would be his matchmaker
有机会要亲自做个媒
and arrange him a good marriage.
给他找个好姻缘
However,
不过
he has you now.
现在有你了
Wait.
等一等
What do you mean?
什么就有我了
Do I have anything to do with it?
跟我有什么关系啊
I haven't found the right one for him.
也没替他找到合适的
It's a pity.
就是可惜
I always feel
总觉得
he deserves a fairy.
他该配天上仙女
Let's go.
走吧
Already?
这就走了
Do you want to come with us?
小雀儿要不要跟我们一起
Mr. Xu.
徐哥哥
I have
我刚才
got your things off my mind just now.
已经把你的事放下了
What things?
放哪儿了
So I can't go with you.
所以我就不能跟你走了
It may not be a bad idea.
留这儿也好
We're in a hurry.
这次时间太紧
When I get back,
等我出行回来
I'll come to see you.
再来找你
OK.
好
I'll wait for you.
我等你
It's a deal.
一言为定
What's up?
怎么了
I feel sorry for you.
我替你可惜
You don't even know
你都不知道
you've missed a fairy.
仙女你都错过了
It's a favor to you.
便宜你了
What have I missed?
我错过什么了
What's the favor?
怎么就便宜你了
Stop asking.
别问了
Is it what your mother left to you?
这是你娘给你的
Daliang Dragon and Sparrow.
大凉龙雀
My mother's sword.
我娘的佩剑
You practice blade instead of sword, don't you?
你不是学刀的吗
This is also the betrothal present
这也是我娘
to my future wife.
给我将来媳妇的聘礼
Isn't it a little dangerous
拿剑做聘礼
to use a sword as betrothal present?
有点凶险吧
Take it.
给
What're you doing?
你干吗
You're my maid.
你是我丫鬟啊
Shouldn't you hold it for me?
你不替我捧剑
Or do you want me to hold it myself?
还要我自己拿着啊
That's what you mean.
是这意思
What do you think?
不然呢
Never mind.
没不然
Where's your aunt?
你姑姑呢
She can't walk me out,
姑姑不能送我出去
otherwise our relationship will be disclosed.
不能泄露我和姑姑的关系
We have to let people think
要让天下人觉得
Qingyang Sect and I are enemies.
我与青阳派为敌
Yeah, I get it.
我明白
You can't go out from the gate.
所以你也不能从大门走
It's strange
我进青阳派
if I leave the enemy's place
背一个剑匣子出去
with a sword box.
说不过去吧
So what?
所以呢
You'd better go out by the side door,
所以你从侧门走
walk along the woods to the mountain road ahead.
从林子里绕到前面山路去
I'll let the carriage wait for you at the corner.
我让马车在拐角等你
What about 10 coins?
十文行不行
20.
二十
Deal.
成交
I should ask for more, shouldn't I?
我是不是要少了
No.
不对啊
Wait.
等会儿
Remember.
你记住啊
Walk along the woods.
贴着林子走
Don't go into the mountain.
千万别进山
I'm not a fool.
我又不傻
I know the way.
能不认路吗
Keep it in your mind.
你记好了
He is out.
出来了
What you've done to me today,
今日所赐
I'll keep it in my mind.
徐凤年铭记在心
Just wait.
你且等着
One day,
终有一日
I'll return to Mount Qingcheng.
我会重返清城
Let him go.
让他走吧
Is this the right way?
是这边吧
It sounds like
听这吼声
the beast is cornered.
像是遇到了绝境
It's strange.
奇怪了
Which beast dares to
什么怪兽
fight Hukui?
敢和虎夔争斗呢
Grandpa Wei, Qingniao.
魏爷爷 青鸟
Come with me to the woods.
随我进林
Why isn't there any sound of birds?
怎么鸟叫都没了
Xu Fengnian.
徐凤年
Is that you?
是你吗